A. Philip Randolph Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
A. Philip Randolph Papers 1909-1979 1941-1968
MSS49775
Randolph, A. Philip (Asa Philip), 1889-1979
13,000 items
56 containers plus 4 oversize
23.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Labor union official and civil rights leader. Correspondence, documents relating to presidential executive orders, memoranda, notes, printed matter, reports, scrapbooks, speeches, and other material reflecting Randolph's role in the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, the Fair Employment Practices Committee, marches on Washington for employment and equal rights for African Americans, and the civil rights movement.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alves, Hazel--Correspondence.; Brown, Theodore E.--Correspondence.; Burton, Charles Wesley, 1887- --Correspondence.; Church, Roberta--Correspondence.; Dodson, Thurman L.--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Granger, Lester B. (Lester Blackwell), 1896-1976--Correspondence.; Green, William, 1870-1952--Correspondence.; Hedgeman, Anna Arnold, 1899-1990--Correspondence.; Hoffman, Anna Rosenberg, 1902-1983--Correspondence.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Correspondence.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968--Correspondence.; Logan, Rayford Whittingham, 1897-1982--Correspondence.; Muravchik, Emanuel--Correspondence.; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952--Correspondence.; Owen, Chandler, 1889-1967--Correspondence.; Randolph family.; Randolph, A. Philip (Asa Philip), 1889-1979.; Reeves, Cleveland H.--Correspondence.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970--Correspondence.; Reynolds, Grant--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Springer, Maida--Correspondence.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968--Correspondence.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972--Correspondence.; Walker, Wyatt Tee--Correspondence.; White, Walter, 1893-1955--Correspondence.; Wilkins, Roy, 1901-1981--Correspondence.; Williams, Aubrey Willis, 1890-1965--Correspondence.
Organizations
A. Philip Randolph Institute. A "freedom budget" for all Americans; budgeting our resources, 1966-1975, to achieve "freedom from want."; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters.; March on Washington Movement (Organization).; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; National Educational Committee for a New Party.; Negro American Labor Council.; Prayer Pilgrimage for Freedom (1957: Washington, D.C.); United States. Committee on Fair Employment Practice.; White House Conference: "To Fulfill These Rights" (1966: Washington, D.C.); Youth March for Integrated Schools (1958: Washington, D.C.)
Subjects
African American labor union members.; African Americans--Civil rights.; African Americans--Economic conditions.; African Americans--Politics and government.; African Americans--Social conditions.; Civil rights demonstrations--United States.; Civil rights--United States.; Discrimination in employment--United States.; Economic assistance, Domestic--United States.; Pan-Africanism.; Race discrimination--United States.; Socialism.
Places
United States--Armed Forces--African Americans.; United States--Race relations.
Titles
Messenger.
Occupations
Civil rights leaders.; Labor leaders.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Asa Philip Randolph, labor union and civil rights leader, were acquired by the Library of Congress in three installments. The first group of papers came to the Library in 1983 as a bequest from A. Philip Randolph via the A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, the second as a gift of from the A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund, also in 1983, and the third was purchased in 1984.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
Other material relating to A. Philip Randolph is in the Manuscript Division's collection of the records of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of A. Philip Randolph are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Online Content
An item from the A. Philip Randolph Papers, "Why Should We March?"; flyer, circa 1941, is available on the Library of Congress website at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms005004.001.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1889, Apr. 15 Born, Crescent City, Fla.
1911 Moved to Harlem, New York, N.Y.
1912 Attended the College of the City of New York, New York, N.Y.
1914 Married Lucille E. Campbell (died 1963)
1917 1928 With Chandler Owen helped found, edit, and publish the Messenger
1918 Joined the Socialist Party Arrested for speaking out against American participation in World War I, Cleveland, Ohio
1920 Organized the Friends of Negro Freedom
1925 Organized the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters Called on President Calvin Coolidge to protest the lynching and plight of African Americans
1925 1968 International president, Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters
1935 Won the right to represent the sleeping car porters with the Pullman Co.
1936 Founding president, National Negro Congress
1937 Negotiated the first wage agreement with the Pullman Co.
1941 Organized the March on Washington Movement Helped persuade President Franklin D. Roosevelt to issue Executive Order 8802 establishing the Fair Employment Practices Committee
1943 Helped persuade President Franklin D. Roosevelt to issue Executive Order 9346 establishing a new Fair Employment Practices Committee
1948 Encouraged President Harry S. Truman to issue Executive Orders 9980 and 9981 creating a Fair Employment Board and a President's Committee on Equality of Treatment and Opportunity in the Armed Services
1951 Conference with President Harry S. Truman led to Executive Order 10210 forbidding racial discrimination by government contractors
1953 Consultation between Randolph and other civil rights leaders and President Dwight D. Eisenhower led to Executive Order 10479 reconstituting the contract compliance agency and placing it under the chairmanship of the vice president
1955 Advised President Dwight D. Eisenhower to issue Executive Order 10590 establishing the President's Committee on Government Policy to enforce a nondiscrimination policy in federal employment Persuaded the AFL-CIO to outlaw racial discrimination
1957 1968 Vice president, AFL-CIO
1959 Founded the Negro American Labor Council
1963 National director, March on Washington
1964 Established the A. Philip Randolph Institute Awarded Presidential Medal of Freedom
1964 1968 Influenced the passage of legislation establishing the civil rights and the voting rights acts
1966 Chairman, White House Conference "To Fulfill These Rights"
1979, May 16 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Asa Philip Randolph (1889-1979) span the years 1909-1979, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1941-1968. The collection comprises the following series: Family Correspondence of Lucille Randolph with her husband and documents relating to her death; General Correspondence; a Subject File which includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, and other documents relating to the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, the Fair Employment Practices Committee (FEPC), and the March on Washington Movement; a Speeches and Writings File; a Biographical File; and Miscellany including address books, appointment books, awards, press releases, printed matter, scrapbooks, travel documents, and other material.
Although there is little material relating to Randolph's career before 1941, the collection highlights his life's work of more than sixty years as an African American union leader and civil rights advocate. The papers reflect Randolph's dedication to securing political, social, and economic rights for African Americans and illustrate the means he favored to accomplish these goals. The General Correspondence, Subject File, and Speeches and Writings File document Randolph's strategy for obtaining his goals. Numerous letters, speeches, and articles reveal his concept of mass protests and passive resistance without violence emulating the tactics of Mohandas K. Gandhi in the struggle for India's independence from Great Britain. Before implementing his strategy of mass protests and passive resistance by means of picketing and the March on Washington Movement, Randolph sought the advice of friends, African American leaders, educators, and organizations concerning his strategy for obtaining political, social, and economic freedom for African Americans. When some of the leadership, including that of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, withheld support, Randolph became convinced that he needed to reach the masses.
Randolph was successful in implementing the tactics of a massive march. On June 25, 1941, Franklin Roosevelt signed Executive Order 8802 which provided for the first Fair Employment Practices Committee (FEPC). Further pressure led Roosevelt to issue Executive Order 9346 on May 27, 1943, establishing a new FEPC, whose jurisdiction included all employment by government contractors and whose authority was expected to encompass discrimination in labor union membership as well as discrimination in employment. The papers document the FEPC until it expired in 1946. The papers also show the NAACP's eventual support for Randolph by donating funds and, in later years, through other methods of cooperation.
Documents relating to the aftermath of a White House meeting, March 22, 1948, between President Harry S. Truman and Randolph and other African American leaders reveal that Randolph and Grant Reynolds threatened civil disobedience if African Americans were forced to register for a compulsory military draft, and on March 31, 1948, Randolph and Reynolds initiated a civil disobedience campaign against military discrimination. Truman issued Executive Orders 9980 and 9981 on July 26, 1948, creating a Fair Employment Board to combat racial discrimination in Federal employment and a President's Committee on Equality of Treatment and Opportunity in the Armed Services. The civil disobedience threat was called off. During the Korean War, Truman issued Executive Order 10210 forbidding discrimination by government contractors and Executive Order 10308 creating the President's Committee on Government Contract Compliance. Executive orders during the administration of Dwight D. Eisenhower include the issuance on August 13, 1953, of Executive Order 10479 reconstituting the Contract Compliance Agency and placing it under the chairmanship of the vice president, and the issuance on January 18, 1955, of Executive Order 10590 establishing the President's Committee on Government Policy to enforce a nondiscrimination policy in federal employment.
The Subject File also includes information on the African American labor movement. Financial and legal papers, correspondence, and other material, 1925-1978, relate to the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters founded by Randolph and others in 1925. The Messenger, a magazine founded and edited by Randolph and Chandler Owen in 1917, was converted into the Black Worker, which became the official organ of the brotherhood. Also in the Subject File are papers documenting the Pullman Company's refusal to recognize the union as a bargaining agent for the porters and maids of the railroad companies. Subsequently, Randolph, as president of the union, petitioned the National Mediation Board, the Arbitration Board, and the Interstate Commerce Commission and won recognition for the union. In 1935, he succeeded in having the Pullman porters classified as railroad men, thereby entitling them to all associated benefits, and on August 25, 1937, the Pullman Company signed its first agreement with its porters, attendants, and maids.
The collection also relates to other topics that Randolph considered to be vital to African Americans, such as the relationship of African Americans to Africa. In 1962, the American Negro Leadership Conference on Africa was formed with Randolph and Martin Luther King, Jr., as co-chairs. Its purpose was to coordinate relations between African Americans and Africa. Other topics highlighted in this collection include the Prayer Pilgrimage held in Washington, D.C., May 17, 1957; the Youth March for Integrated Schools, October 25, 1958; the Negro American Labor Council, 1960-1968, founded by Randolph; National Educational Committee for a New Party, 1946-1947; the White House Conference "To Fulfill These Rights," 1965-1966; and the "Freedom Budget for All Americans," 1966-1967, a ten-year program conceived by Randolph as a means of abolishing poverty in the United States. Some documents indicate that Randolph in later life believed that the time was over for mass marches and demonstrations such as the one he had proposed in 1941 and the one he had organized and led in 1963 for freedom and jobs. As a result of his successes with the labor unions and with presidents from Roosevelt to Johnson, he was convinced that quiet negotiations and consultations should be sufficient.
Correspondents include Hazel Alves, Theodore E. Brown, Charles Wesley Burton, Roberta Church, Thurman L. Dodson, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Lester B. Granger, William Green, Anna Arnold Hedgeman, Anna Rosenberg Hoffman, Hubert H. Humphrey, Maida Springer Kemp, Lyndon B. Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Martin Luther King., Jr., Rayford Whittingham Logan, Emanuel Muravchik, Philip Murray, Chandler Owen, Cleveland H. Reeves, Walter Reuther, Grant Reynolds, Eleanor Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Norman Thomas, Harry S. Truman, Wyatt Tee Walker, Walter Francis White, Roy Wilkins, and Aubrey Willis Williams.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Family Papers, 1942-1963
General Correspondence, 1926-1978
Subject File, 1909-1978
Speeches and Writings File, 1917-1978
Biographical File, 1945-1979
Miscellany, 1920-1979
Oversize, 1920-1946
Container List
- Family Papers, 1942-1963 (Box 1)
  Correspondence of Lucille Randolph with her husband and documents relating to her death.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1942-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Death of Lucille Randolph, 1963
- General Correspondence, 1926-1978 (Box 1-3)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, memoranda, and miscellaneous attachments.
  Arranged chronologically and therein alphabetically by name of person or organization.
  - 1926-1953, (14 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1954-1964, (11 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1965-1978, undated, (15 folders) (Box 3)
- Subject File, 1909-1978 (Box 3-35)
  Correspondence, court cases and agreements, memoranda, legal and financial papers, minutes of meetings and conferences, reports and drafts, newspaper clippings, notes, printed and near-print material, proceedings, and related material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and therein chronologically.
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, formation and bylaws, 1965, undated (Box 3)
  - A. Philip Randolph Park Improvement Association, certificate, 1970
  - Africa
    - American Committee on Africa, 1954-1969
    - American Negro Leadership Conference, 1962-1967
    - Americans for South African Resistance, 1952-1953
    - Correspondence, 1949-1968, undated (Box 4)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1947
  - Barbados trip, 1966
  - Bethel African Methodist Episcopal Church, New York, N.Y., 1958-1973
  - Birthday wishes and tributes, 1954-1977, (3 folders)
  - Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (Box 5)
    - Agreements, 1937-1972, undated, (6 folders)
    - Assignments, New York Central Lines, 1949
    - Banquets, 1965-1975
    - Biennial conventions
      - 1940
      - 1948
      - 1950, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - Black Worker, 1943-1966
    - Colored Locomotive Firemen, 1945-1951, undated
    - Conference for Colored Locomotive Firemen, 1941
    - Conference for Santa Fe and Union Pacific Chair Car Attendants, 1964
    - Constitution and general rules, 1946-1975
    - Correspondence
      - Alves, Hazel, 1943-1944, undated
      - Blanchette, A. R., 1966-1968
      - Bowe, William H., 1966-1968 (Box 7)
      - Bradley, E. J., 1941-1950, undated
      - Brown, Theodore, 1949-1951
      - Dellums, C. L., 1941-1977, undated, (5 folders)
      - McLaurin, Benjamin F., 1942-1951, undated (Box 8)
      - McNeal, T. D., 1941-1970, (3 folders)
      - Miscellaneous, 1925-1975
      - Patterson, Thomas T., 1941-1944, undated, (2 folders)
      - Settles, Eugenia, 1942-1943, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Seymour, W. W., 1973-1978, undated
      - Shackelford, L. J., Jr., 1966-1972
      - Smith, Bennie, 1941-1961, undated, (6 folders)
      - Thompson, L. B., 1972-1975 (Box 10)
      - Totten, Ashley, 1942-1963, undated
      - Webster, Milton P., 1940-1963, (3 folders)
      - Wilds, Bernice Greene, 1952-1958
    - Emergency Board No. 106, brief, 1954
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Year, 1975
    - Financial papers
      - Account books, 1926, undated
      - Ladies Auxiliary, report, 1965-1968
      - Miscellany, 1954-1976
      - Rates of pay, 1952-1967, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 11)
      - Receipts and expenditures, 1966-1971, (2 folders)
      - Report, 1975
      - Statements, 1971-1974, (9 folders)
      - Wage scales, rules, and instructions, undated
    - First National Conference of Dining Car Employees, proceedings, 1937
    - Grievances and inquiries, 1949-1977, undated
    - History, 1928-1978, undated, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - International Executive Board, minutes, 1951-1977, (6 folders)
    - Ladies Auxiliary
      - Biennial convention, 1948
      - Miscellany, 1938-1975
      - Triennial conventions (Box 13)
        - 1956
        - 1965
        - 1968
    - Legal papers
      - Agreements and court cases, 1927-1933, undated
      - Brief, 1926
      - Railway labor disputes and settlements
        - 1933-1964, (5 folders)
        - 1964-1972, undated, (5 folders) (Box 14)
      - Storeroom nonclerical employees cases, 1950, undated, (2 folders)
      - Train maids' case, 1951
    - Lists, undated (Box 15)
    - Local divisions, Pullman Co. lists, 1959-1969, undated, (2 folders)
    - Merger, 1977-1978
    - Midwestern Labor Conference, 1940
    - National Conference of Red Caps, proceedings, 1938
    - National Railroad Adjustment Board, 1967
    - Penn Parlor Attendants program, twentieth anniversary, 1977
    - Pullman Co. porters and maids, digest and argument for working agreement, undated
    - Railway passenger service, 1959
    - Reorganization of the Pullman Co., 1927
    - St. Louis Southwestern Regional Zone Conference, 1943
    - Southern Labor Conference, 1942
    - Triennial conventions
      - 1953, (2 folders)
      - 1959
      - 1962 (Box 16)
      - 1965
      - 1968
      - 1971
    - Union Pacific Chair Car Attendants Conference, 1949
    - Wage and rules case, 1963, (3 folders)
  - Christmas messages, 1950-1970, undated
  - Commission on Inquiry into the Black Panthers and Law Enforcement, 1969-1970
  - Committee of Conscience Against Apartheid, 1966
  - Committee to End Jim Crow in the Armed Services (Box 17)
    - Circulars, memoranda, and lists, 1943-1950, undated, (5 folders)
    - Correspondence
      - 1945-1949, (5 folders)
      - 1950-1951, undated (Box 18)
    - Finances, 1948-1950
    - Legal cases, 1943-1952, undated
    - Miscellany, 1947-1948
    - Printed matter, 1948-1950
  - Conference of Negro Leaders, 1965, undated
  - Democratic and Republican Party platforms, proposals, 1948-1958, undated
  - Dinner and convention invitations, 1961-1970
  - Emergency Committee for Unity on Social Problems, 1961-1962 (Box 19)
  - European trip, 1951-1952, (2 folders)
  - Fair Employment Practices Committee (FEPC)
    - Circulars, 1945-1946, undated
    - Clippings, 1943-1951, undated
    - Conferences, 1943-1952, undated
    - Constitution, principles, and prospectus, 1945, undated
    - Correspondence
      - 1941-1943, (3 folders)
      - 1944-1946, (11 folders) (Box 20)
      - 1947-1950, (10 folders) (Box 21)
      - 1951-1959, undated, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - Executive orders, drafts, 1941-1950
    - Financial papers
      - Bank statements, expenditures, and canceled checks, 1943-1951, undated
      - Contributions, 1944-1951, (4 folders)
      - Correspondence, 1944-1950 (Box 23)
    - History, 1951
    - House of Representatives, 1909-1955, undated
    - Meetings, 1943-1951
    - Membership, 1944-1947, undated
    - Miscellany, 1945-1951, undated
    - Press releases, 1941-1951, undated
    - Printed matter, 1941-1951, undated, (2 folders)
    - Proposed bills, 1944-1951 (Box 24)
    - Report to the nation, 1945
    - Senate, 1944-1949, undated
    - Support, 1942, undated
  - Florida real estate, 1959-1978
  - "Freedom Budget for All Americans," A. Philip Randolph Institute proposal
    - Drafts of proposal, 1966
      - Third
      - Fourth
    - Miscellany, 1966-1967
  - General Electric strike, 1969-1970, undated
  - Health records, 1936-1968
  - In Friendship Committee, 1956-1957
  - International Ladies Garment Workers' Union, congressional investigation, 1962
  - Israel, 1964-1975
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr.
    - Committee to defend, 1960
    - Tribute, 1960-1961
  - Labor (Box 25)
    - Civil rights in the AFL-CIO
      - Memorandum, 1961
      - Miscellany, 1955-1968, undated, (2 folders)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1977, undated, (2 folders)
    - Press releases, 1956-1967
    - Virginia State AFL-CIO Convention, 1961
    - West Indian Movement, 1951-1960, undated, (2 folders)
  - Lincoln Village, Columbus, Ohio, 1954-1955 (Box 26)
  - March on Washington (1963)
    - Jobs and Freedom, 1963-1978
    - Signed support, 1963, (7 folders)
  - March on Washington Movement
    - Cases of discrimination, 1941-1945, undated
    - Circulars, 1941-1944
    - Conferences, 1941-1943, undated
    - Correspondence
      - 1941
      - 1942, (1 folder); (4 folders) (Box 27)
      - 1943, (5 folders)
      - 1944-1947, undated, (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - Financial papers, 1941-1944, undated
    - Lynn, Winifred, case, 1943, undated
    - Membership, 1941, undated
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. case, 1944, undated
    - Minutes of meetings, 1941-1943, undated
    - Miscellany, 1941-1945, undated
    - Press releases, 1942-1946, undated (Box 29)
    - Principles and structures, 1941-1944, undated
    - Printed matter, 1941-1944, undated, (2 folders)
    - Research inquiries, 1955-1971
    - "We Are American Too" Conference, 1943, undated
  - Mayor's Board on Transfer of Relief Administration, Committee on Negro Problems, 1937, undated
  - Membership in clubs and other organizations, 1943-1973
  - Messenger, 1919-1977, undated See also Oversize
  - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. policy, 1919 (Box 30)
  - National Educational Committee for a New Party
    - Aims and principles, undated
    - Announcements of meetings, 1946-1947, undated
    - Finances, 1947, undated
    - Minutes of meetings, 1946-1947, undated
    - Miscellany, undated
    - Printed matter, 1944-1946, undated
    - Statements, undated
  - National Negro Congress, 1936-1951
  - Negro American Labor Council
    - Black Labor in the 1960s: The Negro American Labor Council, by
      - Mark J. Newman, thesis, 1976
    - Convention, 1962, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Miscellany, 1960-1968, undated